<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>err &amp;err</title><link href="http://www.erranderr.com/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.erranderr.com/blog/feeds/automation.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.erranderr.com/blog/</id><updated>2016-07-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Untangling WebDriver and the Browser Automation Landscape I Live In</title><link href="http://www.erranderr.com/blog/webdriver-ontology.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-07-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Maja Frydrychowicz</name></author><id>tag:www.erranderr.com,2016-07-12:blog/webdriver-ontology.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This piece is about too few names for too many things, as well as a kind of origin story for a web standard. For the past year or so, I&amp;#8217;ve been contributing to a Mozilla project broadly named Marionette &amp;#8212; &lt;a href="http://vakila.github.io/blog/marionette-act-i-automation/"&gt;a set of tools for automating and testing Gecko-based browsers like Firefox&lt;/a&gt;. Marionette is part of a larger browser automation universe that I&amp;#8217;ve managed to mostly ignore so far, but the time has finally come to make sense of&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main challenge for me has been nailing down imprecise terms that have changed over time. From my perspective, &amp;#8220;Marionette&amp;#8221; may refer to any combination of two to four things, and it&amp;#8217;s related to equally vague names like &amp;#8220;Selenium&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;WebDriver&amp;#8221;&amp;#8230; and then there are things like &amp;#8220;FirefoxDriver&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;geckodriver&amp;#8221;. Blargh. Untangling&amp;nbsp;needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aside: integrating a new team member (like, say, a volunteer contributor or an intern) is the best! They ask big questions and you get to teach them things, which leads to filling in your own knowledge. Everyone&amp;nbsp;wins.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;W3C&lt;/span&gt; WebDriver&amp;nbsp;Specification&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so let&amp;#8217;s work our way backwards, starting from the future. (&amp;#8220;The future is now.&amp;#8221;) We want to remotely control browsers so that we can do things like write &lt;a href="https://github.com/davehunt/bedrock/blob/e1580816fcedbd3e6fc7d7b95a06270d6cd4f08e/tests/functional/test_navigation.py#L12-L23"&gt;automated tests for the content they run&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://www.hskupin.info/2016/06/02/firefox-ui-tests-platform-operations-project-of-the-month/"&gt;tests for the browser &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt; itself&lt;/a&gt;. It sucks to have to write the same test in a different way for each browser or each platform, so let&amp;#8217;s have a common interface for testing all browsers on all platforms. (Yay, open web standards!) To this end, a group of people from several organizations is working on the &lt;a href="https://w3c.github.io/webdriver/webdriver-spec.html"&gt;WebDriver Specification&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main idea in this specification is the &lt;strong&gt;WebDriver Protocol&lt;/strong&gt;, which provides a platform- and browser- agnostic way to send &lt;a href="https://w3c.github.io/webdriver/webdriver-spec.html#list-of-endpoints"&gt;commands&lt;/a&gt; to the browser you want to control, commands like &amp;#8220;open a new window&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;execute some JavaScript.&amp;#8221; It&amp;#8217;s a communication protocol&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; where the payload is some &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JSON&lt;/span&gt; data that is sent over &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt;. For example, to tell the browser to navigate to a url, a client sends a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;POST&lt;/span&gt; request to the endpoint &lt;code&gt;/session/{session id of the browser instance you're talking to}/url&lt;/code&gt; with body &lt;code&gt;{"url": "http://example.com/"}&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The server side of the protocol, which might be implemented as a browser add-on or might be built into the browser itself, listens for commands and sends responses. The client side, such as a Python library for automating browsers, send commands and processes the&amp;nbsp;responses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This broad idea is already implemented and in use: an open source project for browser automation, Selenium WebDriver, became widely adopted and is now the basis for an open web standard. Awesome! (&lt;em&gt;On the other hand, oh no! The overlapping names begin!&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Selenium&amp;nbsp;WebDriver&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where does this WebDriver concept come from? You may have noticed that lots of web apps are tested across different browsers with &lt;a href="http://www.seleniumhq.org/"&gt;Selenium&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8212; that&amp;#8217;s precisely what it was built for back in 2004-2009&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. One of its components today is &lt;strong&gt;Selenium WebDriver&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Confusingly&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, the terms &amp;#8220;Selenium Webdriver, &amp;#8220;Webdriver&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;Selenium 2&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;Selenium&amp;#8221; are often used interchangeably, as a consequence of the project&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.aosabook.org/en/selenium.html"&gt;history&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selenium WebDriver provides APIs so that you can write code in your favourite language to simulate user actions like&amp;nbsp;this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;client.get(&amp;quot;https://www.mozilla.org/&amp;quot;)
link = client.find_element_by_id(&amp;quot;participate&amp;quot;)
link.click()
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Underneath that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt;, commands are transmitted via &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JSON&lt;/span&gt; over &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt;, as described in the previous section. A fair name for the protocol currently implemented in Selenium is &lt;strong&gt;Selenium &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JSON&lt;/span&gt; Wire Protocol&lt;/strong&gt;. We&amp;#8217;ll come back to this distinction&amp;nbsp;later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, we need a server side that understands incoming commands and makes the browser do the right thing in response. The Selenium project provides this part too. For example, they wrote &lt;strong&gt;FirefoxDriver&lt;/strong&gt; which is a Firefox add-on that takes care of interpreting WebDriver commands. There&amp;#8217;s also InternetExplorerDriver, AndroidDriver and more. I imagine it takes a lot of effort to keep these browser-specific &amp;#8220;drivers&amp;#8221;&amp;nbsp;up-to-date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Then something cool&amp;nbsp;happened&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A while after Selenium 2 was released, browser vendors started implementing the Selenium &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JSON&lt;/span&gt; Wire Protocol themselves! Yay! This makes a lot of sense: they&amp;#8217;re in the best position to maintain the server side and they can build the necessary behaviour directly into the&amp;nbsp;browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It started with &lt;a href="https://seleniumhq.wordpress.com/2011/02/09/operadriver_released/"&gt;OperaDriver&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href="https://dev.opera.com/blog/operadriver-now-a-part-of-selenium-and-experimental-android-support-2/"&gt;2009-2011&lt;/a&gt;, and then others followed such as &lt;a href="https://sites.google.com/a/chromium.org/chromedriver/"&gt;ChromeDriver&lt;/a&gt; and Mozilla&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/geckodriver"&gt;geckodriver&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Mozilla/QA/Marionette"&gt;Marionette&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This is where the motivation for a WebDriver standard comes&amp;nbsp;from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;Review&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selenium Webdriver (a.k.a. Selenium 2, WebDriver) provides a common &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt;, protocol and browser-specific &amp;#8220;drivers&amp;#8221; to enable browser automation. Browser vendors started implementing the Selenium &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JSON&lt;/span&gt; Wire Protocol themselves, thus gradually replacing some of Selenium&amp;#8217;s browser-specific drivers. Since WebDriver is already being implemented by &lt;a href="http://www.theautomatedtester.co.uk/blog/2016/the-final-major-player-is-set-to-ship-webdriver.html"&gt;all&lt;/a&gt; major browser vendors to some degree, it&amp;#8217;s being turned into a rigorous web standard, and some day all browsers will implement it in a perfectly compatible way and we&amp;#8217;ll all live happily ever&amp;nbsp;after.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the Selenium &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JSON&lt;/span&gt; Wire Protocol the same as the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;W3C&lt;/span&gt; WebDriver protocol? Technically, no. The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;W3C&lt;/span&gt; spec is describing the future of WebDriver&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but it&amp;#8217;s based on what Selenium WebDriver and browser vendors are already doing. The goal of the spec is to coordinate the browser automation effort and make sure we&amp;#8217;re all implementing the same interface; each command in the protocol should mean the same thing across all&amp;nbsp;browsers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Fresh Look at the Marionette&amp;nbsp;Family&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I understand the context, my view of Marionette&amp;#8217;s components is much&amp;nbsp;clearer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marionette Server together with &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/geckodriver"&gt;geckodriver&lt;/a&gt; make up Mozilla&amp;#8217;s implementation of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;W3C&lt;/span&gt; WebDriver&amp;nbsp;protocol.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marionette Server is built directly into Firefox (into the Gecko rendering engine) and it speaks a slightly different protocol. To make Marionette truly WebDriver-compatible, we need to translate between Marionette’s custom protocol and the WebDriver protocol, which is exactly what geckodriver does. The Selenium client can talk to geckodriver, which in turn talks to Marionette&amp;nbsp;Server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As I mentioned earlier, the plan for Selenium 3 is to have geckodriver replace Selenium&amp;#8217;s FirefoxDriver. This is an important change: since FirefoxDriver is a Firefox add-on, it has limitations and is &lt;a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Add-ons/Extension_Signing"&gt;going to stop working altogether&lt;/a&gt; with future&amp;nbsp;releases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://marionette-client.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;Marionette Client&lt;/a&gt; is Mozilla&amp;#8217;s official Python library for remote control of Gecko, but it&amp;#8217;s not covered by the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;W3C&lt;/span&gt; WebDriver spec and it&amp;#8217;s not compatible with WebDriver in general. Think of it as an alternative to Selenium&amp;#8217;s Python client with Gecko-specific features. Selenium + geckodriver should eventually replace Marionette Client, including the Gecko-specific&amp;nbsp;features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Marionette project also includes tools for integrating with Mozilla&amp;#8217;s intricate test infrastructure: &lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Marionette_Test_Runner"&gt;Marionette Test Runner&lt;/a&gt;, a.k.a. the Marionette test harness. This part of the project has nothing to do with WebDriver, really, except that it knows how to run tests that depend on Marionette Client. The runner collects the tests you ask for, takes care of starting a Marionette session with the right browser instance, runs the tests and reports the results.&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:6" rel="footnote"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, &amp;#8220;Marionette&amp;#8221; may refer to many different things. I think this ambiguity will always make me a little nervous&amp;#8230; Words are hard, especially as a loose collection of projects evolves and becomes unified. In a few years, the terms will firm up. For now, let&amp;#8217;s be extra careful and specify which piece we&amp;#8217;re talking&amp;nbsp;about. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AutomatedTester"&gt;David Burns&lt;/a&gt; for patiently answering my half-baked questions last week, and to James Graham and &lt;a href="https://sny.no"&gt;Andreas Tolfsen&lt;/a&gt; for providing detailed and delightful feedback on a draft of this article. Bonus high-five to &lt;a href="http://vakila.github.io/"&gt;Anjana Vakil&lt;/a&gt; for contributions to Marionette Test Runner this year and for inspiring me to write this post in the first&amp;nbsp;place. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terminology lesson: the WebDriver protocol is a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wire_protocol"&gt;wire protocol&lt;/a&gt; because it&amp;#8217;s at the application level and requires several applications working together.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I give a range of years because Selenium WebDriver is a merger of two projects that started at different times.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abbreviated Selenium history and roadmap: Selenium 1 used an old &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; and mechanism called SeleniumRC, Selenium 2 favours the WebDriver &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JSON&lt;/span&gt; Wire Protocol, Selenium 3 will officially designate SeleniumRC as deprecated (&amp;#8220;LegRC&amp;#8221;, harhar), and Selenium 4 will implement the authoritative &lt;span class="caps"&gt;W3C&lt;/span&gt; WebDriver spec.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of my claims about Marionette are confirmed by this &lt;a href="http://www.theautomatedtester.co.uk/blog/2012/marionette-the-future-of-firefoxdriver-in-selenium.html"&gt;historical artifact from 2012&lt;/a&gt;, which I came across shortly before publishing this post.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, until recently Selenium WebDriver only included commands that are common to all browsers, with no way to use features that are specific to one. In contrast, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;W3C&lt;/span&gt; WebDriver spec allows the possibility of &lt;a href="https://w3c.github.io/webdriver/webdriver-spec.html#dfn-extension-commands"&gt;extension commands&lt;/a&gt;. Extension commands are being implemented in Selenium clients right now! The future is now!&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fun fact: Marionette is not only used for &amp;#8220;Marionette Tests&amp;#8221; at Mozilla. The client/server are also used to instrument Firefox for other test automation like mochitests and Web Platform Tests. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="mozilla"></category><category term="foss"></category><category term="web"></category><category term="automation"></category></entry><entry><title>Not Testing a Firefox Build (Generic Tasks in TaskCluster)</title><link href="http://www.erranderr.com/blog/taskcluster-generic-tasks.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-05-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Maja Frydrychowicz</name></author><id>tag:www.erranderr.com,2016-05-02:blog/taskcluster-generic-tasks.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few months ago I wrote about my &lt;a href="http://www.erranderr.com/blog/taskcluster-learning.html"&gt;tentative setup&lt;/a&gt; of a TaskCluster task that was neither a build nor a test. Since then, gps has implemented &lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!searchin/mozilla.dev.platform/generic$20task/mozilla.dev.platform/bNYp2HDyeqU/tg4mnGHEAwAJ"&gt;&amp;#8220;generic&amp;#8221; in-tree tasks&lt;/a&gt; so I &lt;a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1227367#c116"&gt;adapted my initial work&lt;/a&gt; to take advantage of&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Triggered by file&amp;nbsp;changes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All along I wanted to run some in-tree tests without having them wait around for a Firefox build or any other dependencies they don&amp;#8217;t need. So I originally implemented this task as a &lt;a href="http://www.erranderr.com/blog/taskcluster-learning.html#scheduling_summary"&gt;&amp;#8220;build&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; so that it would get scheduled for every incoming changeset in Mozilla&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;repositories. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But forget &amp;#8220;builds&amp;#8221;, forget &amp;#8220;tests&amp;#8221; &amp;#8212; now there&amp;#8217;s a third category of tasks that we&amp;#8217;ll call &amp;#8220;generic&amp;#8221; and it&amp;#8217;s exactly what I&amp;nbsp;need. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/mozilla-central/diff/e4ea9261d5bb/testing/taskcluster/tasks/branches/base_jobs.yml"&gt;base_jobs.yml&lt;/a&gt; I say, &amp;#8220;hey, here&amp;#8217;s a new task called &lt;code&gt;marionette-harness&lt;/code&gt; &amp;#8212; run it whenever there&amp;#8217;s a change under (branch)/testing/marionette/harness&amp;#8221;. Of course, I can also just trigger the task with try syntax like &lt;code&gt;try: -p linux64_tc -j marionette-harness -u none -t none&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the task is triggered, a chain of events&amp;nbsp;follows: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;marionette-harness&lt;/code&gt; is defined by &lt;a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/mozilla-central/file/e4ea9261d5bb/testing/taskcluster/tasks/tests/harness_marionette.yml"&gt;harness_marionette.yml&lt;/a&gt;, which depends on &lt;a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/mozilla-central/file/e4ea9261d5bb/testing/taskcluster/tasks/harness_test.yml"&gt;harness_test.yml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/mozilla-central/file/e4ea9261d5bb/testing/taskcluster/tasks/harness_test.yml"&gt;harness_test.yml&lt;/a&gt; says to run &lt;a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/mozilla-central/diff/e4ea9261d5bb/testing/docker/desktop-build/bin/build.sh"&gt;build.sh&lt;/a&gt; with the appropriate mozilla branch and&amp;nbsp;revision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/mozilla-central/file/e4ea9261d5bb/testing/taskcluster/tasks/tests/harness_marionette.yml"&gt;harness_marionette.yml&lt;/a&gt; sets more environment variables and parameters for build.sh to use (&lt;code&gt;JOB_SCRIPT&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;MOZHARNESS_SCRIPT&lt;/code&gt;,&amp;nbsp;etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So build.sh checks out the source tree and executes &lt;a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/mozilla-central/diff/e4ea9261d5bb/testing/taskcluster/scripts/tester/harness-test-linux.sh"&gt;harness-test-linux.sh&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;code&gt;JOB_SCRIPT&lt;/code&gt;)&amp;#8230;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#8230;which in turn executes &lt;a href="https://hg.mozilla.org/mozilla-central/file/1e0b4e27bd51/testing/mozharness/scripts/marionette_harness_tests.py"&gt;marionette_harness_tests.py&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;code&gt;MOZHARNESS_SCRIPT&lt;/code&gt;) with the parameters passed on by&amp;nbsp;build.sh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;For Tasks that Make Sense in a gecko Source&amp;nbsp;Checkout&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I made the &lt;code&gt;build.sh&lt;/code&gt; script in the &lt;code&gt;desktop-build&lt;/code&gt; docker image execute an arbitrary in-tree &lt;code&gt;JOB_SCRIPT&lt;/code&gt;, and I created &lt;code&gt;harness-test-linux.sh&lt;/code&gt; to run mozharness within a gecko source&amp;nbsp;checkout. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why not the desktop-test&amp;nbsp;image?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we can also run arbitrary mozharness scripts thanks to the configuration in the desktop-test docker image! Yes, and all of that configuration is geared toward testing a Firefox binary, which implies downloading tools that my task either doesn&amp;#8217;t need or already has access to in the source tree. Now we have a lighter-weight option for executing tests that don&amp;#8217;t exercise&amp;nbsp;Firefox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why not&amp;nbsp;mach?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my lazy work-in-progress, I had originally executed the Marionette harness tests via a simple call to mach, yet now I have this crazy chain of shell scripts that leads all the way mozharness. The mach command didn&amp;#8217;t disappear &amp;#8212; you can run Marionette harness tests with &lt;code&gt;./mach python-test ...&lt;/code&gt;. However, mozharness provides clearer control of Python dependencies, appropriate handling of return codes to report test results to Treeherder, and I can write a job-specific script and&amp;nbsp;configuration.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="mozilla"></category><category term="foss"></category><category term="ci"></category><category term="automation"></category><category term="taskcluster"></category></entry></feed>