<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Maja Z. Frydrychowicz</title><link href="http://majazf.ca/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://majazf.ca/blog/feeds/events.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://majazf.ca/blog/</id><updated>2014-06-30T09:18:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Open Source Bridge 2014</title><link href="http://majazf.ca/blog/osb14.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-30T09:18:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Maja Z. Frydrychowicz</name></author><id>tag:majazf.ca,2014-06-30:blog/osb14.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Open Source Bridge 2014 was my first conference experience in about 5 years and my first non-academic conference. It had a great mix of talks and was thoughtfully organized and super friendly. I learned about Firefox quality assurance, communication strategies, remote work, discrimination in the tech industry and being a better human. That mix could have been totally different though: during almost every session, there were 3-4 interesting talks competing for my attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attendees were welcome to help out with conference logistics and encouraged to organize spontaneous, open meetings. For example, I spent a couple of hours volunteering as a session chair, which amounts to helping each speaker set up for their talk, introducing them and giving them timing cues. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liz and I also set up a table at the conference Hacker Lounge to introduce potential contributors to Firefox quality assurance and One and Done. We ended up supporting four people as they each set up a development environment for One and Done. As expected, each participant ran into snags along the way with things like database configuration so it was good to work on this in a group. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had encountered most of these setup issues myself before, so it felt awesome to share my experience and speed up their setup process. I think the fact that One and Done was my first Django experience helped a lot: when someone is new to a project, having expert mentors is great but in many cases it's much easier to pose questions and relate to someone who is just a bit less of a beginner than you are. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That particular Hacker Lounge session got me thinking about how easy it is for potential contributors to get discouraged by setup alone. A good readme is priceless! The One and Done readme is quite detailed and helpful, but based our experience at the Hacker Lounge, we will likely add a setup guide or dev FAQ to the projet wiki for additional support. It's silly for someone to miss out on contributing just because they're having trouble installing mysql! &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="mozilla"></category><category term="foss"></category><category term="opw"></category><category term="events"></category></entry></feed>